{
  "questions":[
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "In Coulomb's electrostatic law, two charges are separated by:",
      "correct_answer": "(d) none of these",
      "options": [
          "(a) 1 meter",
          "(b) 1 kilometer",
          "(c) 1 millimeter",
          "(d) none of these"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "The value of the permittivity of free space is:",
      "correct_answer": "(d) all of these",
      "options": [
          "(a) 8.854 × 10^-12 C^2/N·m^2",
          "(b) 4π × 10^-7 N/A^2",
          "(c) 1/(4πε₀)",
          "(d) all of these"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Which of the following relations is correct?",
      "correct_answer": "(d)",
      "options": [
          "(a) F = k * q₁ * q₂ / r²",
          "(b) F = m * a",
          "(c) E = mc²",
          "(d) E = k * q / r²"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Why is a positively charged object made neutral by someone touching it?",
      "correct_answer": "(a) Electrons flow from the object",
      "options": [
          "(a) Electrons flow from the object",
          "(b) Electrons flow onto the object",
          "(c) Protons flow from the object",
          "(d) Protons flow onto the object"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "If the distance between two charges increased by 1/3 times and the magnitude of charge increased by 2 times each, then the Coulomb force is:",
      "correct_answer": "(c) Increased by 36 times",
      "options": [
          "(a) Decreased by 4 times",
          "(b) Increased by 4 times",
          "(c) Increased by 36 times",
          "(d) Remains the same"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "If the distance between two charges is doubled and the magnitude of each charge is doubled, then the electrical force is:",
      "correct_answer": "(d) Increased by 9 times",
      "options": [
          "(a) Doubled",
          "(b) Remains the same",
          "(c) Increased four times",
          "(d) Increased by 9 times"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Compute the Coulomb's force between two charges of 10 C and 100 C in air at a distance of 100 cm:",
      "correct_answer": "(b) 90 N",
      "options": [
          "(a) 9 N",
          "(b) 90 N",
          "(c) 9.0 N",
          "(d) None of these"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Compute the electric intensity in air at a distance of 100 cm from a point charge of 1 C:",
      "correct_answer": "(c) 9 N/C",
      "options": [
          "(a) 1 N/C",
          "(b) 4π N/C",
          "(c) 9 N/C",
          "(d) 0.01 N/C"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "How many electrons are contained in 1 C charge?",
      "correct_answer": "(a) 6.242 × 10^18 electrons",
      "options": [
          "(a) 6.242 × 10^18 electrons",
          "(b) 1 electron",
          "(c) 1 million electrons",
          "(d) 1 billion electrons"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Which of the following statements is correct?",
      "correct_answer": "(a) Coulomb's electrical force is much greater than gravitational force.",
      "options": [
          "(a) Coulomb's electrical force is much greater than gravitational force.",
          "(b) Coulomb's electrical force is much less than gravitational force.",
          "(c) The value of Coulomb's constant (K) is independent of the medium.",
          "(d) Coulomb's force is applicable for long-range distances."
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "If we introduce a dielectric material between two static charges, the electrical force:",
      "correct_answer": "(c) Decrease",
      "options": [
          "(a) Increase",
          "(b) First increase and then decrease",
          "(c) Decrease",
          "(d) Remains the same"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Which of the following is not a unit of electric intensity?",
      "correct_answer": "(d) Volt",
      "options": [
          "(a) Newton/Coulomb",
          "(b) Volt/meter",
          "(c) N/C",
          "(d) Volt"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "If two equal charges, each of 1 C, were separated in air by a distance of 1 Km, what would be the force between them?",
      "correct_answer": "(c) 9 kN",
      "options": [
          "(a) 9 N",
          "(b) 90 N",
          "(c) 9 kN",
          "(d) 9 MN"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Which of the following is a unit of flux density?",
      "correct_answer": "(b) Joule/Coulomb",
      "options": [
          "(a) N/m",
          "(b) Joule/Coulomb",
          "(c) Newton",
          "(d) Tesla"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "The intensity of an electric field at a particular point is greater if an electric charge experiences:",
      "correct_answer": "(a) Greater force",
      "options": [
          "(a) Greater force",
          "(b) Less force",
          "(c) Zero force",
          "(d) None of these"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Three charges, each of 3 µC, are placed at three corners of a square, and the diagonal is 6 cm long. Find the field intensity at the point of intersection.",
      "correct_answer": "(b) 3 N/C",
      "options": [
          "(a) 0 N/C",
          "(b) 3 N/C",
          "(c) 6 N/C",
          "(d) 9 N/C"
      ]
  },
  {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "Which of the following is correct about electric intensity?",
      "correct_answer": "(a) The direction of electric intensity is perpendicular to the electric force.",
      "options": [
          "(a) The direction of electric intensity is perpendicular to the electric force.",
          "(b) The direction of electric intensity is that of the electric force.",
          "(c) The electric intensity is a scalar quantity.",
          "(d) All of these"
      ]
  },
  
    {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "If the distance between the two charged bodies is halved, the force between them becomes:",
      "correct_answer": "(a) Doubled",
      "options": [
        "(a) Doubled",
        "(b) Half",
        "(c) Four times",
        "(d) One half"
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "The value of permittivity for free space is:",
      "correct_answer": "(b)",
      "options": [
        "(a) 8.85 x 10^-12 F/m",
        "(b) 8.854 x 10^-12 F/m",
        "(c) 1",
        "(d) 2.998 x 10^8 m/s"
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "The SI units of permittivity are:",
      "correct_answer": "(b)",
      "options": [
        "(a) C/N",
        "(b) F/m",
        "(c) N/m^2",
        "(d) A/m^2"
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "If the distance between two charges is doubled, the electric force between them will become:",
      "correct_answer": "(c) Half",
      "options": [
        "(a) Four times",
        "(b) Twice",
        "(c) Half",
        "(d) One fourth"
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "The minimum charge on any object cannot be less than:",
      "correct_answer": "(a) Elementary charge (e)",
      "options": [
        "(a) Elementary charge (e)",
        "(b) Proton charge",
        "(c) Electron charge",
        "(d) Neutron charge"
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Physics",
      "type": "multiple",
      "difficulty": "medium",
      "question": "The electric force between two charges placed in air is 2 Newton. When placed in a medium, the force reduces to:",
      "correct_answer": "(c) 0.025 Newton",
      "options": [
        "(a) 0.019 Newton",
        "(b) 0.029 Newton",
        "(c) 0.025 Newton",
        "(d) 0.03 Newton"
      ]
    },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The potential of all the points of equipotential planes is:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Same",
        "options": [
          "(a) Same",
          "(b) Zero",
          "(c) Different",
          "(d) Infinite"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Tick the correct statement:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Two equipotential surfaces cannot intersect each other",
        "options": [
          "(a) Two equipotential surfaces can intersect each other",
          "(b) Two equipotential surfaces cannot intersect each other",
          "(c) They intersect sometimes",
          "(d) None of these"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Equipotential surfaces in an electric field are always:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Perpendicular to electric lines of force",
        "options": [
          "(a) Tangent to electric lines of force",
          "(b) Perpendicular to electric lines of force",
          "(c) Closed surfaces",
          "(d) Uniformly spaced"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Capacitor is a device used for:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Storing electric charge",
        "options": [
          "(a) Storing direct current",
          "(b) Storing electric charge",
          "(c) Storing alternate current",
          "(d) Storing voltage"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "For a capacitor, the charge per unit volt is called:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Capacitance",
        "options": [
          "(a) Charge density",
          "(b) Dielectric constant",
          "(c) Permittivity",
          "(d) Capacitance"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Farad is the unit of:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Capacitance",
        "options": [
          "(a) Charge",
          "(b) Current",
          "(c) Potential",
          "(d) Capacitance"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "A capacitor is a perfect insulator for:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Direct current",
        "options": [
          "(a) Direct current",
          "(b) Alternating current",
          "(c) Both for direct and alternating current",
          "(d) Electric charge"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The value of the capacitance depends upon the:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Geometry of the capacitor",
        "options": [
          "(a) Thickness of the capacitor plates",
          "(b) Charge on the plates",
          "(c) Voltage applied",
          "(d) Geometry of the capacitor"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The charge on the capacitor depends upon:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Voltage applied",
        "options": [
          "(a) Voltage applied",
          "(b) Distance between the plates",
          "(c) Area of the plates of the capacitor",
          "(d) Density of the surface of the capacitor"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Capacitance of a parallel plate capacitor does not depend upon:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Nature of the material of the plates",
        "options": [
          "(a) Separation of the plates",
          "(b) Area of the plates",
          "(c) Medium between the plates",
          "(d) Nature of the material of the plates"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Due to electric polarization of dielectric, the capacity of a capacitor:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Increases",
        "options": [
          "(a) Decreases",
          "(b) Increases",
          "(c) Remains the same",
          "(d) Becomes zero"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Two equal and opposite charges separated by a small distance are said to constitute a:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Dipole",
        "options": [
          "(a) Insulator",
          "(b) Superconductor",
          "(c) Mass number",
          "(d) Dipole"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The electric intensity outside the two oppositely charged parallel metal plates is:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Zero",
        "options": [
          "(a) Zero",
          "(b) Maximum",
          "(c) Minimum",
          "(d) Infinite"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Electric intensity inside the hollow sphere is:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Zero",
        "options": [
          "(a) Minimum",
          "(b) Maximum",
          "(c) Zero",
          "(d) Zero"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The negative of the potential gradient is:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Electric field intensity",
        "options": [
          "(a) Electrostatic force",
          "(b) Electromotive force",
          "(c) Potential difference",
          "(d) Electric field intensity"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "In RC series circuit the time during which the capacitor acquires 0.63 times the equilibrium charge is known as:",
        "correct_answer": "(c) Time constant",
        "options": [
          "(a) Growth constant",
          "(b) Decay constant",
          "(c) Time constant",
          "(d) Infinity"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The speed of charging or discharging a capacitor depends upon the product of resistance and:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) current",
        "options": [
          "(a) current",
          "(b) Capacitance",
          "(c) Potential difference",
          "(d) Charge"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "A resistor - capacitor, the energy resides in:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) The field between the plates",
        "options": [
          "(a) The negative plate",
          "(b) The positive plate",
          "(c) Both the positive and negative plate",
          "(d) The field between the plates"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "In a charged capacitor, the energy resides in:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) The field between the plates",
        "options": [
          "(a) The negative plate",
          "(b) The positive plate",
          "(c) Both the positive and negative plate",
          "(d) The field between the plates"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "If time constant in C-R circuit is small, the capacitor is charged or discharged:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Rapidly",
        "options": [
          "(a) Rapidly",
          "(b) Slowly",
          "(c) At a constant rate",
          "(d) Intermittently"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Coulomb/Volt is called:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Joule",
        "options": [
          "(a) Electron",
          "(b) Farad",
          "(c) Ampere",
          "(d) Joule"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Electric flux due to point charge q present inside a closed surface can be deduced using:",
        "correct_answer": "(c) Gauss's law",
        "options": [
          "(a) Coulomb's law",
          "(b) Ohm's law",
          "(c) Gauss's law",
          "(d) Lenz's law"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Two similar charges, each of one coulomb placed in air one meter apart repel each other with a force:",
        "correct_answer": "(c) 1 N",
        "options": [
          "(a) 1 N",
          "(b) 1 N",
          "(c) 1 N",
          "(d) 1 N"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The unit of capacitance is:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Farad",
        "options": [
          "(a) Farad",
          "(b) Coulomb per ampere",
          "(c) Volt per meter",
          "(d) Ampere per volt"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The equivalent capacitance is greater than individual capacitance:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Parallel combination",
        "options": [
          "(a) Series combination",
          "(b) Parallel combination",
          "(c) Series and parallel combination",
          "(d) All of these"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Farad is defined as:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Coulomb/volt",
        "options": [
          "(a) Coulomb/volt",
          "(b) Ampere/volt",
          "(c) Coulomb/joule",
          "(d) Joule/coulomb"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Unit of capacitance is:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Coulomb per volt",
        "options": [
          "(a) Coulomb per volt",
          "(b) Volt per meter",
          "(c) Coulomb",
          "(d) Ohm"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Identify the practical application of electrostatic induction:",
        "correct_answer": "(c) Laser",
        "options": [
          "(a) Inkjet printer",
          "(b) X-rays",
          "(c) Laser",
          "(d) MRI"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Another name for dielectric is:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Insulator",
        "options": [
          "(a) Conductor",
          "(b) Insulator",
          "(c) Semiconductor",
          "(d) Superconductor"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "If a charged body is moved against the electric field, it will gain:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Electrical potential energy",
        "options": [
          "(a) Potential energy",
          "(b) Kinetic energy",
          "(c) Mechanical energy",
          "(d) Electrical potential energy"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Electrical field intensity at a point is defined by the equation:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) E = q/F",
        "options": [
          "(a) E = q/r",
          "(b) E = F/q",
          "(c) r = Qf",
          "(d) E = q/F"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The intensity of electric field between two oppositely charged parallel plates close to each other is:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Zero",
        "options": [
          "(a) Zero",
          "(b) Maximum",
          "(c) Minimum",
          "(d) Infinite"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Electric lines of force can never:",
        "correct_answer": "(c) Intersect each other",
        "options": [
          "(a) Repel each other",
          "(b) Attract each other",
          "(c) Intersect each other",
          "(d) All of these"
        ]
      },

      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The word \"Xerography\" means:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Dry writing",
        "options": [
          "(a) To take a photograph",
          "(b) Dry writing",
          "(c) Writing by a machine",
          "(d) To paint the same thing"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "Identify the practical application of electrostatic induction:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) All of these",
        "options": [
          "(a) Inkjet printer",
          "(b) X-rays",
          "(c) Laser",
          "(d) All of these"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The effective capacitance is reduced when capacitances are connected in:",
        "correct_answer": "(a) Series",
        "options": [
          "(a) Series",
          "(b) Parallel",
          "(c) Series-parallel combination",
          "(d) None of these"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "In Millikan method, each drop has the charge of:",
        "correct_answer": "(c) Integral multiple of minimum value",
        "options": [
          "(a) Same value",
          "(b) Different values",
          "(c) Integral multiple of the minimum value",
          "(d) Zero value"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The product of resistance and capacitance is:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Time",
        "options": [
          "(a) Velocity",
          "(b) Force",
          "(c) Acceleration",
          "(d) Time"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "The dot product of electric field and vector area is called:",
        "correct_answer": "(b) Electric flux",
        "options": [
          "(a) Electrical potential",
          "(b) Electric flux",
          "(c) Potential gradient",
          "(d) Magnetic field"
        ]
      },
      {
        "category": "Physics",
        "type": "multiple",
        "difficulty": "medium",
        "question": "For the computation of electric flux, the surface area should be:",
        "correct_answer": "(d) Spherical",
        "options": [
          "(a) Flat",
          "(b) Curved",
          "(c) Inclined",
          "(d) Spherical"
        ]
      }
    ]
  }